<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>J.F.'s reply unto Thomas Crisp's rapsody of lies, slanders and defamations of J.F. and R.R. &amp;c. entituled, The fifth part of Babel builders, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F864C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789308</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2641:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>J.F.'s reply unto Thomas Crisp's rapsody of lies, slanders and defamations of J.F. and R.R. &amp;c. entituled, The fifth part of Babel builders, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: John Feild [i.e. John Field].</note>
                  <note>Date and place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent. --  Babel's-builders unmask't. --  Part 5.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>J. F's Reply UNTO <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi>'s Rapſody of Lies, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Defamations of <hi>J. F.</hi> and <hi>R. R.</hi> &amp;c. Entituled, <hi>The Fifth Part of Babel Builders,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>An unjuſt man is an Abomination to the Juſt, and he that is upright in the way, is an abomination to the wicked.</p>
                  <p>There is a Generation whoſe Teeth are Swords, and their Jaw Teeth as Knives to devour the Poor from the Earth, and the needy from among men.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>The Soul of the wicked deſireth Evil: and his Neighbours findeth no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in his eyes,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 21.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>Who whet their Tongue like a Sword, and bend their bow to ſhoot their Arrows, even bitter words,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.3.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>To the Reader, ſhewing in brief our preſent Exerciſe is not new.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Courteous READER,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Thought meet to remind thee how that Enmity and wroth ſoon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Heart of <hi>Cain</hi> againſt his innocent Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe his offering was not accepted. And there was a <hi>Korah,</hi> a <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> that pretended to holineſs, tho' wicked men, and roſe up againſt that meek man <hi>Moſes, Numb. 16.</hi> And there was a <hi>Rabſhekeh,</hi> that was highly conceited of himſelf no doubt, when with vain words he ſaid, <hi>I have Councel and Strength,</hi> &amp;c. and ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſaid to me, Go up againſt this Land and deſtroy it, 2</hi> Kings <hi>18, 19.</hi> But the Virgin Daughter of <hi>Zion</hi> deſpiſed him, ſhak'd her head at him, and laughed him to ſcorn; and they that are in the ſame Spirit, now are his Off-ſpring, for all their high words and pretences, of being the <hi>Chriſtian Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. There was alſo, we read, a <hi>Judas</hi> that betrayed his Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and falſe Brethren among the Apoſtles that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172617:2"/>did then as <hi>T. C.</hi> doth now prate againſt the Truth; yea, there were ſome that brought in damnable Doctrines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and I ſhall leave thee to Judge whether this man is not in the ſame Spirit, and inſtigated by him (out of whoſe Mouth came the unclean Spirits like Froggs; ſee <hi>Rev. 16.13.</hi>) to belye, ſlander, and miſ-repreſent the Friends of Truth and People of the Lord in this our Age, to whom I wiſh Repentance, to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his Fault, and remain thy Friend <hi>J. F.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>And now I ſhall apply my ſelf to <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Thomas Criſp,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have ſeen a Paper of thine, wherein it plainly appears to me, thou haſt in thy pride and wrath ſaid, <hi>viz. For</hi> J. F. <hi>and</hi> R.R. <hi>they are ſuch inconſiderable Perſons, that I am almoſt aſhamed that I have taken any notice of them. Anſw.</hi> Well, <hi>Thomas,</hi> thou maiſt be quite and altogether aſhamed of thy belying, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and defaming of us; but I perceive <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid true, <hi>A Fools mouth is his deſtruction, and his lips the ſnare of his Soul, and proud and haughty Scorner is his Name, that dealeth in proud wrath: for wrath killeth the fooliſhman, and envy ſlayeth the ſillyone. But remember better is the poor that walketh in his uprightneſs; than he that is perverſe in his waies, though he be rich.</hi> And if thou <hi>T. C.</hi> art rich and wiſe in thy own conceit, them that thou accounteſt poor, <hi>have underſtanding, and have ſearched thee, and find there is more hopes of a Fool</hi>— But as inconſiderable as we be, if <hi>T.C.</hi> or any other can bring the man, that can prove, that ever either of us had any thing of any but what we came honeſtly by (and without begging) or laboured for, or received of any one Farthing or Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things worth, directly or indirectly for Preaching, for every Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they ſhall have two; for though we have and do Adminiſter as occaſion ſerves, we do not receives. Through the Lord's bleſſing there is no need. And truly, it thou art a rich man, it's pity thou ſhould be ſo malicious and fooliſh to turn Informer as thou doſt (in publick Print, and in the very Title page of thy Book) againſt an inconſiderable Perſon too in thy eſteem, ſure thou waſt more mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than wiſe herein, for what couldſt thou expect to gain of ſuch an one. Well, this is no new thing, for when the <hi>Devil</hi> could not have his will of <hi>Job,</hi> to lead him into wickedneſs, nor prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172617:2"/>on him to make him Anſwer his mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he turned <hi>Informer</hi> againſt him: ſo thou maiſt ſee and read who is the father of all mercenary and ungodly, malicious <hi>Informers;</hi> and what became of Rich <hi>Haman</hi> that inform'd againſt poor <hi>Mordecai</hi> (and ſought the deſtruction of the people he belonged to, and told lies to effect it) though a better man than himſelf, though not ſo <hi>Rich.</hi> Thou calleſt thy Book, <hi>A Reply to ſeveral Lies, Slanders, falſe and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Inſinuations of</hi> R. Richardſon, <hi>and</hi> J. Field<hi>'s Inhabitant and Preacher,</hi> (and then tells where, and the place of his abode) and adds, <hi>of</hi> G. F's <hi>Party.</hi> Pray obſerve the <hi>Informers</hi> Information, and mark his Enmity, for his Book, I may ſay, is ſtuffed with that he falſly pretends it's a Reply unto, <hi>viz.</hi> Lies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with ſome <hi>Billingſgate</hi> (as thou ſaiſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 17.) manners, for thee calls names, as <hi>Drudges, Arrogant Prater, Inquiſitor to the Bull and Mouth, like a lazy begging Fryar, falſe Accuſer, like Mercenary Reformado's, Black Fryer like Fellow; He,</hi> viz. J. F. <hi>may have an Eye to an Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritor or Informers place.</hi> Well, <hi>Thomas,</hi> but what ever eye thou maiſt maliciouſly ſuggeſt I may have, thou haſt taken the <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> place before me; but I will not here tell where thou liveſt, leſt others ſhould hear of this thy new Undertaking. Beſides, I wiſh thou maiſt grow wiſer, tho' I am of the wiſe Man's mind, <hi>That there is more hopes of a Fool, than a man wiſe in his own conceit: for the fooliſhman perverteth his way, and his heart fretteth againſt the Lord;</hi> yea, and his People to, I may ſay, proving <hi>That evil men and Seducers wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being <hi>deceived.</hi>
                  </hi> Thou chargeſt me with a Lie in thy 18 <hi>pag.</hi> for ſpeaking of Friends, and ſaying, <hi>Their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is in the eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> Sure <hi>Thomas</hi> if thee Believes there be any Friends to God and Chriſt, thou muſt grant their Unity is there, or elſe inform me where it is (indeed <hi>pag.</hi> 3. thou ſaiſt, there (quoting <hi>John</hi>) <hi>Their fellowſhip is in the Light;</hi> and what difference is there between the Light (<hi>John</hi> there ſpoke of) and the eternal Spirit. But prethee <hi>Thomas</hi> hear thy ſelf a little further how egregiouſly thou contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts thy ſelf, and Preaches the ſame Doctrine, which thou art an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with me for, <hi>&amp;c. page</hi> 6. thou ſaiſt, <hi>I own all faithful Friends and People of God, their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is in the eternal Spirit:</hi> Very well, <hi>Thomas,</hi> and are not they that are faithful to the Spirit of God, faithful Friends, I will aſſure thee I never meant nor ſaid that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful Friends, or Ranters, and them that be not the People of God, were of one mind, or that their Unity was in the Eternal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172617:3"/>Spirlt. And ſeeing thou ſaiſt, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>Take this Aſſertion not ſtrictly but to the Church or People of God, it ſeems contrary to Scripture,</hi> &amp;c. though thou in the 6. <hi>pag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſays, thou <hi>owns the People of Gods uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in the eternal Spirit.</hi> I ſhall here ſhew that the Apoſtles exhorted the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to be of the ſame mind, and Judgment though <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith, <hi>It ſeems contrary to the Scripture,</hi> and quotes <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. &amp;c. as if the Apoſtles contradicted himſelf, which would be wicked to Aſſert or inſinuate. Now the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. its ſaid <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Diviſions</hi> (or <hi>Schiſms</hi>) <hi>among you; but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame Judgment:</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.5, 6. the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Now the God of patience and conſolation, grant you to be like minded one towards another, according to Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> [or after the Example of him who did wear the ſeamleſs Coat] <hi>That ye may with one mind, and one mouth glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13, 14, 25. yea, the whole Chapter. I think I may ſay if thou was not a Novice (as thou termeſt me) in the Scripture, thou would never have made ſuch a noiſe as thou haſt about this Poſition, but I ſhall leave my Reader to judge whether thou art one of them that thinks to be heard for thy much babling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or whether for this Doctrine thus agreeing with Scripture, and own'd by <hi>T. C.</hi> I (have proved my ſelf <hi>like the wicked Atheiſt, a Lyar, wicked and falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and proud <hi>Boaſter</hi>
                  </hi>) or <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Lie (in the 18 <hi>pag.</hi>) thou chargeſt me with, is for ſaying, <hi>Thou prateſt againſt the Truth.</hi> But if all what thou haſt writ be true, I might acknowledge it ſo, but its not, therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>a falſe Witneſs ſhall not be unpuniſhed; and he that ſpeaketh Lies ſhall periſh;</hi> ſo read thy portion if thou repent not, <hi>For the prating Fool ſhall fall,</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomon.</hi> And, <hi>Thomas,</hi> I will aſſure thee it's not thy thinking this or that, that's any proof, tho' it's thy practice in ſeveral Pages of thy Book ſo to ſay, as rich as thou art, thy word will not be taken herein, I doubt thou art a little pufft up in thy mind with the conceit of thy Riches; well remember its ſaid, <hi>It makes it ſelf wings and flies away;</hi> and therefore do not becauſe of it, aſſume to tell my meaning, and what I think, as in the 13 <hi>page, &amp;c.</hi> for that thou knoweſt not; and therefore in ſo ſaying, thou aſſumes God's Prerogative, who according to <hi>Amos</hi> 4. laſt, ſhews what the thoughts are, and manifeſteſt thy ſelf a Lyar as well as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172617:3"/>Conceited; I don't ſay like <hi>Iriſh</hi>—as thou ſpeaks of, <hi>page</hi> 12. And in thy 4th <hi>Ba. p.</hi> 12. thou ſaiſt, I judge not nor condemn any perſon for their Judgment and practice, that differs from me that is not a breach of the Revealed Will of God, and have often cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified as much. Then pray prove my Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> that Friends Unity <hi>(viz.)</hi> faithful ones, is in that eternal Spirit that leads all them, that are faithful thereunto, to be of one mind (prove I ſay this contrary to the Revealed Will of God if thou canſt) and if their Unity is in it, as thou owneſt, then they are one in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if it be not thus proved the contrary by the Revealed Will of God, without thy thinkings and ſay-ſo's! for alas that won't do, indeed <hi>Tho.</hi> it wont, alſo prove that the names thou call'ſt me and <hi>R.R.</hi> thy ſcoffing Lies and Raylery, in thy Book, is according to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Will of God, which if it be the Scripture thou call'ſt the Revealed Will of God, pray let me have Chapter and Verſe, as thou ſaiſt, <hi>p.</hi> 8.) and as alſo <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> in his confuſed Book) well, <hi>Thomas,</hi> don't think I have here pickt out all thy Lies, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Nick-names, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in thy Rabble of Railery, thou callſt <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels Builders,</hi> &amp;c. no, no, for I queſtion whether all the Paper I have here writ will hold them; but if thou perſiſt, may be I may give a Catalogue of them. But thy Tongue to me doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be that, which is ſaid to be a <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> but rather to be ſet on fire of Hell. So I think I may conclude, and ſay with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, A poor man is better than a Lyar; and he that hath a froward heart findeth no good; and he that hath a perverſe Tongue falleth into miſchief, yea, the fools lips enter into contention, and his mouth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for ſtrokes;</hi> So, <hi>Thomas,</hi> do thou make right application hereof, And take a large meaſure or quantity of unfeigned Repentance, Humility, and the fear of the Lord, and lie ſtill therein until thou haſt felt the righteous Judgments of God brought forth into victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over that Conceitedneſs, Pride and Wrath, which hath ſo much filled thy heart, that it hath bred, as I may ſay, an evil diſeaſe that ſticks faſt unto thy Soul, yea, and the very Scab of Contention; and if this means the Lord inclines thy heart unto, thou maiſt thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Cure: Which that thou maiſt, is my real deſire, if it be God's Will, for I find, through the goodneſs of the Lord, the Spirit of forgiveneſs in my Heart towards thee.</p>
               <p>But if you ſtill remain angry, I am of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s mind, who ſaith, <hi>Make no Friendſhip with an Angry man; and with a furious man thou ſhalt not go.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172617:4"/>
And <hi>Thomas,</hi> thou ſaiſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. ſomething about my having a high conceit of my ſelf, for which thou ſaiſt, thou ſeeſt no cauſe for it, except it's my high living at—where ſaiſt thou, I think thou haſt no cauſe to complain of thy high Rent. Well, <hi>Thomas,</hi> I perceive thou makeſt the Proverb good, <hi>That every Fool will be meddling,</hi> (tho' this concerns thee not) but I would have thee know that I have, and do as honeſtly pay my Rent as thee; and for ought I know, thy dwelling and mine conſidered as much as thou doſt. Well, Duſt it's ſaid is the Serpents meat who creeps upon his Belly, and makes his Followers Back-biters, Lyars, and Creepers like himſelf, and his Children loves the ſame meat, and as greedily feed thereof, when they get it, as is manifeſted by thy collecting the Letters of divers perſons names in thy fourth Page, which, if true, manifeſt thy ſelf, to be one of curſed <hi>Ham</hi>'s brood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I obſerve that thou maliciouſly ſpeaks in thy 5 <hi>page</hi> of ſome, <hi>That have been guilty of evil words and actions, and yet have been owned as God's faithful Servants—and in the Power of God, and adds our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is in forms. Anſw.</hi> Obſerve his words (have been.) But I affirm no perſon in the eternal power of God can be found in evil words and actions, neither can thoſe that are therein, have Unity with ſuch, for all that goes into evil words and actions, goes from the power of God, and are by the ſame power Judged and Condemned; and them that keep in the eternal power of God cannot have Unity with them therein, but if any have gone from the power of God, and they Return and Repent, they may find mercy with God, and have Unity with his faithful people which we deſire, and if thou ſhould ſo do we ſhould greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. And I would have thee conſider, whether thy expoſing the Letters of the Names of thoſe Perſons in <hi>page</hi> 4. doth not prove that thou haſt <hi>in thy Fore-head, the more certain and legible Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of that thou calleſt the Beaſts mark,</hi> viz. <hi>Hatred and Strife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou takeſt little or no notice, as I obſerve, in thy Book of our 20, and 21 Pages of <hi>T. C</hi>'s <hi>Envy Detected,</hi> &amp;c. which ſhews how the <hi>Barbados</hi> Friends have been abuſed by ſome (for ought I know of Party with thee, who got a wrong Copy, not according to the ſence of the Meeting; ſee our Book aforeſaid. Do them Juſtice, and do not abuſe them in Print any more, but if thou doſt, read what they ſay for themſelves, and publiſh it too.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172617:4"/>
Alſo in thy 14. <hi>p.</hi> I find thee angry about my ſaying its thy <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to Pay Tithes and be Married by a Prieſt,</hi> ſaying herein <hi>(as his uſual manner is) Lies be his Refuge,</hi> and in the ſame Page thou ſayſt, I falſly inſert that it was thy Principle to Marry by a Prieſt and pay Tythes, and yet in the ſame Page <hi>thou ſayſt thou asked</hi> J. B. <hi>and my ſelf, whether thy ſelf or another might not Marry by a Prieſt, and pay Tythes,</hi> and to which ſayſt thou <hi>J. B.</hi> ſaid he believed it was my (<hi>viz. T.C</hi>'s.) Principle, to which thou <hi>T. C.</hi> Anſwers, it was, <hi>viz.</hi> that one might Marry by a Prieſt and pay Tythes, and be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Well if this be not thy Principle, why was it thy Practice, was it to manifeſt thy ſelf an Hypocrite, or one that acts contrary to thy Principle? I think if that was all, thou might have ſpared thy pains, at leaſt to many, who have and do know thee: thou askeſt me in the 8. <hi>p. What warrant from Scripture I have to term thy Marriage an Evil?</hi> &amp;c. I anſwer, that when thou according to thy Aſſertion in the 19. <hi>p.</hi> of thy fourth <hi>Babel,</hi> &amp;c. hath proved that there is Preſident and Command in Scripture for what thou didſt in that matter, and for having a Ring, and ſaying after the Prieſt: I ſay when thou haſt proved this, thou mayſt expect to hear more from me. But this I may add, that in the 13. <hi>p.</hi> thou ſay'ſt, <hi>But in caſe I had ſo ſaid,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> that to pay Tythes and Marry by a Prieſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was my Principle) <hi>it doth not follow, that I therefore muſt ſo do.</hi> Well, <hi>Tho.</hi> it ſeems then thou doſt not look upon thy ſelf bound to Act according to what thou ſay'ſt; nay, nay, I am of the mind that's little enough regarded by thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But who is the Quibbler now, which by long, practice is grown expert? Oh, <hi>Tho.</hi> I tell thee, I for ever deſire rather to be a Dunce in ſaying one thing, and doing another, than Expert, except the ſaying hath relation, to ſlander, falſhood and untruth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it would be better not to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ſuch ſayings, though it's too much thy practice in thy confuſed <hi>Babels</hi> ſo to ſay. And in the 13.<hi>p.</hi> thou ſay'ſt, I am angry that thou ſaid'ſt, That Submitting to the Magiſtrates for Conſcience ſake, is accounted Submitting to the Pope. And here <hi>Tho.</hi> thou haſt done worſe than Quibble, thus maliciouſly to inſinuate, as if we accounted Submitting to the Magiſtrate for Conſcience ſake, was a Submitting to the Pope, which is a lying, falſe and wicked Inſinuation, that tends to ſtir up and inſence the Magiſtrate againſt our Friends; and it's ſo much the worſe, at this time, because many lyes under severe and grievous Sufferings, by Impriſonment, and ſpoil of Goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ungodly and unchriſtian Inſinuation thou uſhers in thus,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172617:5"/>15 <hi>p.</hi> 4 <hi>Bab.</hi> It's a wonder to me, when I conſider how many have been incouraged to deny or refuſe Submiſſion to Authority, on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Conſcience: and ſuch accounted faithful and valiant Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but for being ſubject to the Magiſtrate for Conſcience ſake is accounted ſubmitting to the Pope. <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if I did not by thy Scribling find, that the Spirit of Enmity had enter'd thee, and that thou art thereby inſtigated thus to write, I might wonder, that <hi>T.C.</hi> ſhould thus falſly and maliciouſly Inform againſt ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted faithful and honeſt Friends, and inſinuate that they were incouraged to deny or refuſe ſubmiſſion to Authority, under (or on) pretence of Conſcience. And do not the malicious Informers give ſuch like Evidence againſt our peaceable Meetings in the Sp. of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as that they are on pretence or under colour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when the Lord knows it's no truer than what <hi>T. C.</hi> enviouſly ſaith, <hi>viz.</hi> notoriouſly falſe, for we refuſe not ſubmiſſion to Authority in any thing on pretence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in reality, and we are ſubject to Authority either in Active or Paſſive obedience for Conſcience ſake, deſiring <hi>to lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty, making our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Supplications,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for all men, for Kings, and them that are in Authority, knowing that it's good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour, who would have all men ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> And now, <hi>Thomas,</hi> conſider who is the <hi>Forger, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, Maker of Lies, and thy Maſter</hi> (as thou mentions in the 10, and the 13 <hi>pag.</hi>) And whether thou art not in the very practice of <hi>Forging, Informing, and making Lies,</hi> for thy Maſter and Father of Lies; I ſay, Conſider of it, and Repent thereof before it's too late, for <hi>he that ſoweth iniquity ſhall reap vanity, and the Rod of his anger ſhall fail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou haſt not made a litttle Clamour about the Paper writ into the Country, in which it was ſaid at the Concluſion, <hi>viz. and have no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with</hi> T. C. this thou calleſt my Bull of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, tho' the words were uſed in a private Letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, <hi>Thomas,</hi> if it be a Bull of Excommunication for me to ſay, <hi>I have no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with thee;</hi> what is it for thee to ſay <hi>I am of the Synagogue of Satan,</hi> and to compare me to them <hi>Paul</hi> fought with at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> beſides the names mentioned before; nay, in the 13<hi>p.</hi> to render me worſe than a <hi>Cheat, Pick-pocket,</hi> or <hi>Mercenary Reformado,</hi> as thy terms are, for I ſuppoſe thou wilt grant theſe may be defamed as bad as they be; but thy Enmity is ſo great againſt me, that thou ſaiſt, <hi>I cannot defame thee.</hi> To which I Anſwer, <hi>The Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172617:5"/>thee thou falſe and lying Tongue,</hi> and maiſt not be ſaid unto thee, if thou Repent not, <hi>Thou loveſt all devouring words, Oh thou deceitful Tongue, God ſhall likewiſe deſtroy thee for ever, he ſhall take thee away, and pluck thee out of thy dwelling place; and root thee out of the Land of the living; the Righteous alſo ſhall ſee, and fear, and ſhall laugh at him. Lo, this is the man that made not God his ſtrength; but truſted in the abundance of his Riches, and ſtrengthned himſelf in his wickedneſs.</hi> But to return, may not thy calling me of the <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> be termed thy Bull of Excommunication againſt me as well as my ſaying, <hi>I have no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with thee,</hi> Is termed (by thee) my Bull of Excommunication againſt thee. <hi>Who art thou that Judgeſt another and doſt the ſame things?</hi> Well, <hi>he that deviſeth to do evil, ſhall be call'd a miſchievous perſon, and the thought of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs</hi> (it's ſaid) <hi>is ſin, and the ſcorner is an abomination to men,</hi> and in that ſtate I ſhall leave my Reader to view and pity thee. In ſeveral <hi>pages,</hi> as the 1, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thou prateſt of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Party, to which I Anſwer, we diſown all Parties out of Truth, for Truth leads not into Sects, or to be Sect Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thou alſo in many pages termeſt <hi>G. F.</hi> mine, and <hi>R.R.</hi> Maſter, to which I ſay, I own no Maſter, but Chriſt (according to Scripture) <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.10. tho' I own and eſteem <hi>G. F.</hi> as an ancient faithful Friend and Labourer in the Goſpel of Peace, yea, a Father in the Truth to many, and matter not what <hi>T. C.</hi> in his rage and Enmity may ſay, becauſe thereof, who is manifeſting himſelf to be like a raging Wave of the Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and void of Charity, as he ſpeaks in his 4<hi>p.</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding me and many more (for no other cauſe but owning <hi>G. F</hi>'s Spirit) as none of God's Children, and ſo no Chriſtians, tho' I have told him I own <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Spirit,</hi> as govern'd by the Spirit of God; and I am well and fully ſatisfied that <hi>G. F.</hi> ſerves <hi>God with his Spirit in the Goſpel of his Son; and in his wiſdom Acts to the praiſe of his Grace, who is over all, bleſſed for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 7. thou ſaiſt, <hi>I prove not the obſerving any Command of God according to the Scripture, only the impoſing the Imaginations of</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c. on People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thou wouldeſt maliciouſly inſinuate, as if the Ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginations of <hi>G. F. &amp;c.</hi> was impoſed on People, which I deny and charge it upon thee as a wicked ſlander, alſo that any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Holy Scriptures is deſired by us to be practiced by any. Oh, <hi>Thomas,</hi> remember the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>He that ſpeaketh Lies ſhall not dwell in his Houſe,</hi> which thou doſt in <hi>p.</hi> 8. where thou ſpeakeſt of many black Characters given thoſe that—only <hi>for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172617:6"/>diſobedience or Non-conformity to</hi> G. F's <hi>Imaginations or forms,</hi> as if our Unity ſtood in Forms or Imaginations, I tell thee it's not, but in that Eternal Spirit in which all faithful Friends and People of God's Unity ſtands, as thou owneſt, <hi>p.</hi> 6. and it's not thy bare (tho' confident denying us to be ſuch is any proof thereof) or as thou there ſaiſt of our being <hi>Lyars, wicked and falſe Accuſers and proud Boaſters,</hi> but it may ſerve for a proof of the contrary, and of thy Malice and enmity, which that Spirit that luſteth to Envy, hath brought forth in thee; ſo that in <hi>p.</hi> 19. thou art at it again, ſaving, <hi>You be the Authors of Confuſion and Blaſphemy, by contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting the Scriptures, and your own former Teſtimonies in impoſing your own conſtitutions, on your Brethren, contrary to the Light, in their Conſciences, and therein ſetting the Spirit in Oppoſition to it ſelf. Anſw.</hi> Alas, <hi>Thomas,</hi> wouldſt faſten that upon us, which thou art ſo apparently Guilty of in thy Poſition, that the Spirit of God did or might allow one to pay Tithes or Marry by a Prieſt, and that by the ſame Spirit of God another might be required not pay them, or not do the ſame thing; but this Sham won't do, for it's no truer than we are the Authors of Confuſion and Blaſphemy, and impoſe our own Conſtitutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is notoriouſly falſe. Thou ſaiſt in thy 18 <hi>p.</hi> J. F. ſaith, <hi>He hath not griped, nor over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reached any man. To which thou Anſwereſt, I think he hath little op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to do it, having ſo little dealing with men, but I believe he gets or gripes (that is more than covet) as much by</hi> 20 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> worth that he ſells, as I do by</hi> 10 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> worth. Anſw.</hi> Well, <hi>Thomas, I ſee</hi> it's true <hi>that the ungodly man diggeth up evil, and in his lips there is a burning Fire; and a Hypocrite with his mouth deſtroyeth his Neighbour:</hi> —but <hi>deſtruction ſhall be to the workers of Iniquity, for the man that wandereth out of the way of underſtanding, ſhall remain in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Dead,</hi> ſo read thy Station, for I intend to follow the wiſe man's advice, who ſaith, <hi>Let not thy heart Envy ſinners, but be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long.</hi> But I perceive thou wouldeſt be willing to publiſh me if thou couldeſt prove that I had griped or over-reached any man, which ſaiſt thou, for want of proof, I think he hath little opportunity (for he tells his belief in the matter) which is, he gets or gripes more by 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> &amp;c. than I by 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> (which he affirms is more than Covet) ſo that he would inſinuate (with his malicious thought and falſe belief) that I did more than break that Commandment, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Covet,</hi> &amp;c. but by his thus writing, he puts me upon thinking,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172617:6"/>that this came a little near him; for when the ſore place is touched, there is apt to be a winching: But thy <hi>Tongue,</hi> I may ſay, <hi>deviſeth miſchief like a ſharp Raſor, working deceitfully, thou loveſt evil more than good; and Lying rather than to ſpeak Righteouſneſs.</hi> And <hi>Thomas,</hi> thou haſt mentioned <hi>G.F</hi>'s Name (againſt whom thy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſeems to be great) 85. times in thy 2 ſheets and ½ and mine 74. But know, <hi>That every Tongue that riſes up in Judgment againſt the Lord,</hi> in him and his Children (<hi>viz.</hi> the Lords) <hi>God hath given Power to Condemn,</hi> but thy Old Bottle cannot hold no New, but Sower Wine, which the Children of the Lord cannot Drink, for it's no better than the Wine of Fornication, which the Whores Cup was filled withal, whoſe Name was <hi>Myſtery</hi> Babylon, <hi>the great, the Mother of Harlots,</hi> in whoſe Womb of uncleanneſs thy <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> were conceived, and by the ſtrength of her Power brought forth; in whoſe Spirit thou Scoffingly ſpeaks of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Laws and Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But never yet (though often called upon) produced a Catalogue of them, thou ſo clamoureſt againſt and rages at, which if thou dareſt, ſure thou wouldeſt by this time; but, may be thou may conſider if thou ſhouldſt, thy weakneſs, folly and madneſs, would be more manifeſt, for crying, railing and clamouring againſt that which is ſo conſonant to, and agreeable with the Scripture, and Chriſtians commendable practice.</p>
               <p>And in his 1 <hi>page</hi> he ſaith: <hi>But ſeeing its my lot to be beſet with ſuch as</hi> Paul <hi>Fought with at</hi> Epheſus, J. F. <hi>and</hi> R. R. <hi>and I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to acquit my ſelf of them, and their Lyes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and then they are their own, ſeeing they love them ſo well</hi> (viz. <hi>Lyes</hi>) &amp;c. <hi>as to make them their Refuge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Well <hi>Thomas,</hi> paſſing by thy Compariſon, which ſhews thy Envy more than thy Honeſty: I ſhall tell thee, that thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours indeed is, and will be in vain, as to the acquitting thy ſelf of them Untruths and Lyes, which in our former we Charged thee with; for it's not thy laying thy Lyes at our doors will acquit thee from being the Father or Publiſher thereof, nor make them ours, but thou Inſinuates as if we <hi>Loved Lyes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>So well as to make them our Refuge:</hi> Nay, nay, if we loved Lyes, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded we ſhould be better Loved by thee; and as for making them our Refuge, I deny it, for bleſſed be the Lord, we have a better Refuge; even him (that ſhall ſweep away the Refuge of Lyes) who we believe will hide us, <hi>From the ſecret Councel of the wicked, from the Inſurrection of the workers of Iniquity, who make
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172617:7"/>their own Tongue to fall upon themſelves; and all that ſee them ſhall flee away,</hi> Pſal. 64.2, 8.</p>
               <p>Again in his 5 <hi>pag.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I ſhall Anſwer ſome Lyes</hi> J. F. <hi>charges me with,</hi> viz. <hi>In the</hi> 9 <hi>pag. he ſaith, I dealt by him like a wicked Atheiſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here I obſerve thou makeſt ſome do, becauſe the words <hi>(there is)</hi> were taken into the Parentheſis; and ſaith, there then remains only theſe words, <hi>viz. no God:</hi> True, but this Phraſe of Scripture I made uſe of only to ſhew thy abuſe, in leaving out a Material Sentence of mine, that ſhould explain the reſt, as theſe words, <hi>viz. (The Fool hath ſaid in his heart)</hi> explains the following, <hi>viz. there is no God:</hi> Now to leave out the former (as thou didſt by me) would make the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſay, <hi>there is no God:</hi> So this will not yet prove <hi>I. F. a Lyer, nor like the wicked Atheiſt;</hi> the other Lye is, that I ſaid, <hi>Friends <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is in the Eternal Spirit,</hi> which <hi>T.C.</hi> ſaith in the the 5 <hi>pag. Is falſe:</hi> But I do again affirm it's a Lye for thee to ſay, <hi>Our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity is not in the Eternal Spirit, and thou haſt proved to the contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, in the 6 <hi>pag.</hi> thou ſayſt, J. F. <hi>Charges in the</hi> 11 <hi>pag. with Lyes, in ſaying, That they,</hi> viz. S. E. C. T. <hi>&amp;c. have Adored or Worſhipped</hi> G. F. <hi>and his Laws, and that they</hi> (G. F. <hi>his Party</hi>) <hi>do make that the obeying</hi> G. F. <hi>his Laws, can acquit in Gods ſight,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which</hi> (thou ſayeſt) <hi>thou ſhalt leave to the Truth in all to Judge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Truth in me, and many more, judgeth thee a Lyer, and a falſe Accuſer therein, from under which, with all thy Shuffling and wrangling, thou canſt never get, for we utterly diſown all Adoration or Worſhip; to any Creature or Created thing, it (<hi>viz.</hi> Worſhip) being only due to God and Chriſt, and is only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by man and woman in the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>And in the 14 <hi>pag. T. C.</hi> ſaith, <hi>I fear the wicked one was ſo great with you, to Inſtigate you to the publication of this, in hope thereby to make a difference between us, that ſo you might have your deſire on us: But I bleſs God I fear not</hi> G. F<hi>'s whole Black-Guard of Lyars,</hi> R. R. J. F. <hi>and</hi> C. T. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That which he here ſaith, he fears the wicked one Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated us to the publication of, was a Paper or private Letter, which was ſent to a perſon in the Country only to give an Account of him: What he had done, and what he was, and how that he ſtill remains a perſon with whom Friends have not Unity; and to do his Wife Juſtice, Intimated therein, that ſhe had condemned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172617:7"/>it, (<hi>viz.</hi> her being Married by a Prieſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) But this Account hath greatly Angryed the man, that though he pretends to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask others,</hi> would not be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd himſelf,</hi> and therefore calls this Letter or Paper, <hi>A Bull of Excommunication,</hi> &amp;c. and now pretends a ſear which is altogether groundleſs and falſe, <hi>viz. That the wicked one Inſtigated us thereto,</hi> &amp;c. For if we had our deſires, it's only your Eternal well being, and in order thereto, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thou <hi>T.C.</hi> may come to a ſight of thy evil, thou didſt in that Concern, ſo as thou may Judge it, as ſhe did, and that you both may be truly ſenſible of whatſoever elſe you have done that is offenſive to the Lord, and condemn it, that ſo you may come to know Forgiveneſs at the hand of God, and Peace with him, and have Love unto his People, and ſo bear the mark of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt; and now I ſhall leave my Reader to Conſider who belongs to the <hi>Black-guard of Lyars,</hi> &amp;c. (as thy Phraſe is.) And of the Incivility of this man, and how full of Enmity he is, thus to expoſe his own Wife, and render <hi>her deceived,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. for her giving out that Paper, which I am perſwaded was from ſome Inward Senſe ſhe had of that evil ſhe had done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thou ſayeſt (Scoffingly) <hi>Take a view of all the wicked Crew of Confeſſors,</hi> &amp;c. But hadſt thou ſaid, take a view of all the wicked Crew or falſe Accuſers, I think thy Wife might have found thee among them, notwithſtanding my deſire is you may live in that Amity as becomes Man and Wife.</p>
               <p>Again, I find <hi>T. C.</hi> offended at what was Charged upon him in my laſt, (though true) from theſe words of his, <hi>viz. But one Reaſon why I paid that ſo often mentioned as Tythes, was as a witneſs that I was not taught my fear by the Precept of</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c. nor receive his Traditions for Doctrines, and that I had not Sacrificed all my Faith, Conſcience and Judgment to his Orders, your Idol to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that as too many both ſmall and great do: But as a Teſtimony againſt your Impoſition,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To which I Replyed, <hi>Is not this an ungodly Inſinuation is if all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Friends had ſacrificed all their Faith, Conſcience and Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. and this Query he calls my Aſſertion, but takes no notice, that I call'd upon him (and now do again) to prove any of the many, both ſmall and great that ſo do. And I would have the Reader obſerve he grants he paid (that ſo often mentioned) as Tythes, and tells his reaſon for it, though in his 19 <hi>page</hi> he ſaith contrary. And you further evidence your not doing as you would be done
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172617:8"/>by, by your Printing in the three ſeveral Books, <hi>viz. T. C.</hi> ſaid he paid Tythes lately, notwithſtanding it was anſwered to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry before in Print. <hi>Anſ.</hi> hereby I ſuppoſe he would have it thought that he did not pay Tythes, though he ſaid to me in the preſence of <hi>P. E.</hi> that he had lately paid Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and conſented to have it writ and Printed, and took a Copy thereof with him; doth not this man manifeſt himſelf a <hi>Babel Builder, And like the fooliſh woman that pulls down her Houſe with her own Hands.</hi> I remember a Saying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> concerning which I think may be in a great meaſure apply'd to <hi>T. C.</hi> which is, <hi>The fooliſh Woman ſhe is clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ſhe is ſimple and knoweth nothing;</hi> and if <hi>T. C.</hi> knoweth any thing as he ought to know, he practiceth little thereof in his Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble againſt Friends, which alſo brings to my remembrance the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prophet to the ſottiſh Children, <hi>They are wiſe to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge.</hi> And in the 12 <hi>page</hi> ſaith <hi>T. C J. F.</hi> ſaies, <hi>A Remnant are taught not to buy, or receive any of theſe mens corrupt Doctrines, (viz. Books) hereby inſinuating Friends ſhould not read what was writ in detection of them,</hi> &amp;c. To which I Anſwer, I did (and do) ſay that God hath ſo preſerved a Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in his fear, that from him they have received wiſdom, and thereby are taught not to buy or receive any of theſe mens corrupt words and falſe Doctrines, but I did not ſay Books, that's a piece of Forgery, or ſomething like it, of <hi>T.C</hi>'s to annex Books, which when he hath ſlyly foiſted in, he ſaith, <hi>Therefore if you will try all things, and ſee for your ſelves, and not give up all to them, then you are not of one mind, and ſo not of the faithful</hi>—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>charges us with Impudence. Anſw.</hi> Well, it's ſaid, <hi>The wicked worketh a deceitful work;</hi> and I ſhall leave my Reader to judge whether <hi>T. C.</hi> hath not ſo done herein, by adding the word <hi>Books,</hi> and then like a man fighting with his ſhaddow, or one that Beats the Air, he talks or writes; but it's like had he not ſtuffed in or added that word he would have wanted matter to have quarrelled with, but at adding and patching, curtailing, tranſpoſing, and mangling, and miſchievouſly miſplacing, he is more ready than honeſt; ſee his Collection of Teſtimonies, and call'd the third Edition, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet</hi> the 26th of the Fifth Month 82. in his 11 <hi>page,</hi> where he cites <hi>E. B</hi>'s Works, and how groſly he abuſes him (let the Reader ſee and judge) by taking a few words in one place, <hi>viz.</hi> the 852. <hi>p.</hi> and leaving off at a Comma, and then go back thirteen or fourteen lines, and begin at a Semicolon, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172617:8"/>leave off at a Semicolon, and then go forward about 63 <hi>pages</hi> in Folio, to the 889. and takes a few lines more; and then back again about 215 <hi>page</hi> to 594. and all to patch ſomething together, to make it ſpeak as he would have it, by all which he manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to be notwithſtanding his pretences, in that Spirit the <hi>Jews</hi> were in, that cryed up the Prophets, garniſhed their Sepulchers and ſhew him that was the Life of the Prophets, ſo <hi>T. C.</hi> cryes up <hi>J. P. E. B.</hi> &amp;c. and is in that Spirit that would murder the Life that was in them, and is now in and among Friends.</p>
               <p>But I thought not to have ſpent ſo much time about his Railing Book, neither have I taken notice of all I juſtly might; nor par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Anſwered to all them Aſſertions, as he (falſly) calls falſe, but leave them to the unprejudiced with the Truth and Spirit of it to Judge, who all them Names, he calls me and <hi>R. R.</hi> if rightly applyed belong to.</p>
               <p>And laſtly obſerve in his laſt page, he ſeems to Apologize, (as it conſcious to himſelf) for his harſh or ſharp Writing and Expreſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſaith, <hi>They are our Weapons, and ground at our Grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and ſharpened by our ſelves, and as uneaſie as</hi> Saul<hi>'s Armour to</hi> David, <hi>and no more delightful to him than a Wife and Children of Fornication,</hi> &amp;c. To all which I in ſhort Anſwer, If it was true that they were ours, as it's falſe, it might mitigate his fault; but let him prove, if he can, we ever call'd him the Names aforeſaid, <hi>Mercinary Reformado's, Inquiſitor, Black Guard of Lyars,</hi> and many more, and therefore I adviſe him to do by this Old man, with his evil deeds of Lying <hi>&amp;c. As</hi> David <hi>did by</hi> Saul's <hi>Armour, alſo no longer to delight in a Wife and Children of Fornication,</hi> &amp;c. For the Lord hath determined to Plague her, <hi>Whoſe Cup is full of Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Filthineſs of Fornication, and to daſh her Children and Bratts againſt that Stone, which many now are ſtumbling at, for</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon <hi>is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul Spirit, and Cage of every unclean and hateful Bird,</hi> Rev. 18.2. <hi>Yea her Plagues ſhall come in one day, death, and mourning, and famine; and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with fire; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the voice from Heaven is, come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues, for her ſins hath reached unto Heaven, and God hath remembred her Iniquities,</hi> (and therefore wo be unto all <hi>Babel</hi> builders) for ſtrong is the Lord that judgeth her, who will not regard the weeping, the Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor Lamentation of her Merchants, becauſe no man buyeth her Merchandize any more.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172617:9"/>
And <hi>Thomas,</hi> I underſtand thy Books were given away at the Meeting-houſe-doors at <hi>Bull and Mouth</hi> the 14th of the 5th. Month 1682. which to me is one proof more of thy great Enmity as well as Folly, in ſo publickly manifeſting thy Belying and Slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of me and Friends. So that in the words of the Prophet I may conclude, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Thine own wickedneſs ſhall correct thee, and thy back-ſlidings</hi> [and Lyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] <hi>ſhall reprove thee; know there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and ſee that it's an evil thing and bitter, that thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Lord thy God, and that my fear is not in thee, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Thou mayſt take this at preſent, as an Anſwer to thy Railing Book, from thy Belyed and Slandered Friend,</hi> J. Feild, <hi>Junior.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
